Guide to the Ernesto Galarza Papers, 1936-1984
Department of Special Collections
Ernesto Galarza Papers,
1936-1984
Special Collections M0224
Galarza, Ernesto
41.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Correspondence, reports, minutes, legal documents, notes, newsletters, press releases, newsclippings, statistical information, questionnaires and photographs documenting Galarza's career as a labor organizer, scholar, Research Director in the National Agricultural Workers Union (1947-1960), and nationally prominent Mexican American activist.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions on access.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. Ernesto Galarza, 1971-1978.
Biography
Ernesto Galarza was born in Jalcocotan in the state of Nayarit, Mexico, in 1905. In 1910, Ernesto, his mother, and two maternal uncles left their village to find employment and escape the depredations during the Madero Revolt. They spent three years traveling northward before settling in Sacramento, California. During their journey, they spent one year in Mazatlan, Sinaloa, where Galarza began his formal schooling in 1911. Although his mother and one uncle died in an influenza epidemic when Ernesto was only twelve, his other uncle made it possible for him to continue his education. He soon became fluent in English, and took part-time and summer jobs as a messenger, drug store clerk, court interpreter, and field and cannery worker. Following graduation from high school, Galarza entered Occidental College in Los Angeles on scholarship in 1923. He was a member of the debate team, wrote for the school newspaper, did field work in Mexico during his senior year, and was elected to Phi Beta Kappa.
A year after his graduation in 1927, Galarza received a fellowship to study Latin American history and political science at Stanford University. While at Stanford, he married Mae Taylor, a Sacramento teacher. He received the M.A. in 1929, having written a thesis entitled Mexico and the World War (available in the Green Library stacks, and in the Stanford University Archives). He then entered Columbia University to begin a doctoral program in Latin American history.
In the early 1930s, the Galarzas established the Year-Long School, an experimental elementary program on Long Island where students spent the summer working on a farm. He continued to teach, lecture, and write and do research on Latin America for the Foreign Policy Association in New York.
A fellowship enabled him to do field work and write his dissertation, La industria electrica en Mexico (Mexico City: Fondo de Cultura Economica, 1941). He obtained a Ph.D. from Columbia in 1944. Galarza spent nearly eleven years in Washington, D.C., first as research associate in education, and then as Chief of the Division of Labor and Social Information at the Pan-American Union. He was particularly interested in the living conditions of Mexican contract workers, the braceros who first came to the United States on a war-time emergency basis in 1942. By July, 1945, more than 58,000 braceros were working in agriculture, and almost 62,000 were on railroad crews. Galarza traveled to bracero camps and worked to publicize and correct conditions and abuses.
He also was employed by the Bolivian government as a consultant on labor and economic conditions; he later published his findings in The Case of Bolivia (Washington, D.C.: Pan American Union, Inter-American Reports, 1949). He wrote and edited a number of titles in the Inter-American Reports and the Latin America for Young Readers series, published by the Pan-American Union. Galarza left his post with the Pan-American Union in 1947 to become the Director of Research and Education in California for the Southern Tenant Farmer's Union (STFU). The STFU's membership included black and white tenant farmers and agricultural laborers striving for better wages, better working conditions, and more favorable legislation for small-scale farm workers.
Galarza's command of Spanish and personal experience in Sacramento Valley orchards and packing houses made him a valuable asset to the organization, renamed the National Farm Labor Union in 1947. He soon became involved in the union's strike against the DiGiorgio Fruit Corporation, begun in November, 1947 under the direction of Hank Hasiwar. The strike for higher wages, one of the earliest and longest in the history of the San Joaquin Valley, lasted for thirty months before the easy availibility of bracero labor and congressional pressure forced the union to back down. Bitter feelings persisted on both sides; Galarza and the union were entangled in libel suits and countersuits with DiGiorgio for more than fifteen years. (see Boxes 35-43). Galarza and the union were involved in some twenty strikes in the South and the West between 1948 and 1959. Galarza realized the futility of strike actions as long as a large and inexpensive pool of braceros was readily available, either "on loan" from grower to grower, or hurriedly imported from Mexico.
In 1974, he recalled his strategy: One, we had to bring about the termination of the bracero program. We figured it would take us ten years and it did. Our view was that when that was accomplished that we next would have to undertake a similar campaign to bring to the attention of the country and to bring about legislation concerning the wetbacks. Our view was not to exclude the wetbacks. Our view was that the so-called wetback is a product of the social and political conditions of Mexico; and consequently we favored a campaign of publicity, confrontation, documentation, protest and so on that would zero in not on the wetback as a person, but on the Mexican government and its policy in Mexico that created such terrible poverty conditions that the wetback was a natural product of this burgeoning Mexican capitalism. That was our pitch. Maybe that would take us ten years and at the end of that ten year stretch we then thought that we could begin organizing farmworkers. Maybe fortunately or unfortunately, I don't know, that strategy of the union was cut off halfway. We never got to the wetback issue, not really. That brings us to 1960 and the union went down the drain. (Morris, Gabrielle. The Burning Light: Action and Organizing in the Mexican Community in California [Berkeley: Regional Oral History Office, 1982])
As the again renamed National Agricultural Workers Union's finances, support, and staffing declined, the AFL-CIO launched the Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee with Norman Smith as its head. During 1959, Galarza served as a field organizer for AWOC, but jurisdictional disputes among the AFL-CIO leadership and philosophical differences between Galarza and Smith soon led to a parting of the ways. (see Series III) Fearing that the AFL-CIO chiefs would preemptorily order NAWU to relinquish its charter and merge with either the AWOC or the United Packinghouse Workers of America, NAWU president H.L. Mitchell convinced the membership to vote in favor of a merger with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butchers Workmen.
Galarza was soon dissatisfied with the arrangement and left Amalgamated in 1960. The decade of the 1960s found Galarza dividing his time between agricultural labor issues and the concerns of a growing, urban Mexican American population. His book Merchants of Labor, a detailed critique of the fading bracero program, was published in 1964. Congressman Adam Clayton Powell, Chairman of the House Committee on Education and Labor, appointed him chief labor counsel in an investigation into the collision of an overloaded bus and a train in Chualar, California on September 17, 1963, in which thirty-two Mexican nationals were killed. Galarza's report, reissued in 1977 as Tragedy at Chualar: El crucero de las treinta y dos cruces, was a scathing indictment of the safety violations so prevalent in the transport of braceros. (See Series IV)
In the mid-1960s, Galarza was a program analyst for the Economic and Youth Opportunities Agency in Los Angeles. With Herman Gallegos, he served as a consultant to the Ford Foundation on the needs of Mexican Americans, the results of which were later published as Mexican-Americans in the Southwest. The authors provided an assessment of the educational, political, economic and demographic status of what was then the nation's second-largest minority group. Galarza and Gallegos also reviewed grant proposals submitted to the Ford Foundation by Mexican American groups, one of which led to the establishment of the Southwest Council of La Raza in Phoenix.
Increasing recognition of Galarza as one of the country's leading Mexican American intellectuals and activists brought new commitments. He was elected Chairman of La Raza Unida Unity Conference at its organizational meeting in 1967. La Raza Unida began as a loose confederation of Hispanic civic, social, and cultural groups, whose representatives were in El Paso to attend hearings of the Cabinet Committee on Mexican American Affairs. By the time the second major conference took place in San Antonio in January, 1968, La Raza Unida chapters were being organized throughout the United States. During the late 1960s and early 1970s, Galarza also served on the Board of Directors of the Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund (MALDEF), a nationally prominent public interest legal organization. The majority of his time, however, was devoted to teaching and writing. He immersed himself in theories of and strategies for bicultural education.
In 1971, he founded the Studio Laboratory for Bilingual Education, a resource center for students and faculty of the San Jose Unified School District. The Studio Lab stressed a hands-on approach to the teaching of cultural values, nature, and the creative arts. During this time he wrote poems and short stories for use in bilingual classrooms, as well as his autobiography Barrio Boy.
Galarza's teaching excellence earned him several honorary positions, including Distinguished Visiting Professor at San Jose State University, Visiting Professor of Community Development at the University of California, San Diego, Honorary Fellow at U.C. Santa Cruz, and Associate in Mexican American Problems, Harvard Graduate School. Galarza's final book on agriculture, Farm Workers and Agri-business in California, 1947-1960, is a scholarly, personal account of NFLU/NAWU's campaign to organize domestic farm workers, negotiate with agri-business and government officials, repeal pro-bracero legislation, and stem the tide of undocumented workers. (See Box 1, folders 10-12; Box 2, folders 1-5.) In 1971, Galarza received the honorary Doctor of Humane Letters degree from his alma mater, Occidental College. In 1979, Galarza's name was submitted to the Swedish Academy for consideration for the Nobel Prize in Literature. He was the recipient of the Friends of VISTA Award for Exceptional Service and Work to End Poverty in 1980. Ernesto Galarza died in his San Jose home on June 22, 1984.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Galarza Papers reflect the multi-faceted career of activist scholar Ernesto Galarza. The thirty-two linear feet of papers consist of correspondence, reports, minutes, legal documents, notes, newsletters, press releases, newsclippings, statistical information, questionnaires, and photographs dating from 1923 to 1984. The collection is divided into five series: Personal and Biographical Information; Writings of Ernesto Galarza; Organizational Files; Subject Files; and Photographs/Graphic Materials.
The Galarza Papers are particularly rich in information about Mexican and Mexican American farm workers in California from 1948 to 1960. As research director and organizer for the National Agricultural Workers Union during those years, Galarza gathered data and wrote extensively about the living and working conditions of migrant farm workers. Other subject strengths include the development of the National Agricultural Workers Union, other farm labor groups, and non-agricultural organizations, such as El Congreso del Pueblo de Habla Espanola and La Raza Unida. A myriad of other issues are represented in the collection, including employment, bilingual education, immigration, discrimination, poverty programs, and Mexican American culture.
Series Description and Inventory
- Personal and Biographical Information, 1938-1984, Series 1
  The first series contains personal correspondence and newsclippings about Galarza. A notebook which includes Galarza's resume, a list and reviews of his publications, supporting materials and letters of recommendation for the Nobel Prize for Literature, provide an overview of his career.
  - Biographical information, 1950-1979 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical information, newsclippings, 1944-1984 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1938-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Nobel Prize, recommendation for nomination, 1979 (1) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Nobel Prize, recommendation for nomination, 1979 (2) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Nobel Prize, recommendation for nomination, 1979 (3) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Nobel Prize, recommendation for nomination, 1979 (4) (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings of Ernesto Galarza, 1944-1978, Series 2
  Series II consists of articles, notes, outlines, drafts, speeches and legislative testimony presented by Galarza. The bulk of this series pertains to the writing of Strangers in Our Fields, his earliest published denunciation of the bracero program, and Farm Workers and Agri-business in California, 1947-1960.
  - Subseries A. Articles
    - Articles, 1944-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Articles, 1960-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Subseries B. Notes and Drafts for Books
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (1) 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (2) 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (3) 1947-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (4) 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (5) 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (6) 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (7) 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Farmworkers and Agri-business in California,, manuscript notes, (8) 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Merchants of Labor, correspondence and notes, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Spiders in the House, outline, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, correspondence, 1955-1956 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, correspondence, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, field notes, 1952-1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, manuscript draft, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, publicity, 1955-1958 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Strangers in Our Fields, reports, 1957, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Unidentified writings, notes, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries C. Speeches and Legislative Testimony
    - Speeches and legislative testimony, 1944-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Organizational files, 1935-1974, Series 3
  The third series is divided into sections on agricultural and non-agricultural organizations. Both sub-sections are arranged alphabetically by the name of the organization. The organizational files pertaining to agriculture consist largely of records resulting from Galarza's work with the Pan-American Union, the Southern Tenant Farmers Union, the National Agricultural Workers Union, and the Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee.
  Papers from Galarza's tenure at the Pan-American Union (1936-1947) are scanty, since he apparently brought with him to California only records on bracero conditions and policies which might be of use to him there. The Pan-American Union (now known as the Organization of American States) is made up of representatives of American countries and seeks to promote cooperation in foreign trade, finance, agriculture, travel, intellectual and cultural exchange. Galarza's correspondence, statements and reports while Chief of the Division of Labor and Social Information demonstrate his efforts to monitor the Mexican contract labor system from its earliest years, when the majority of braceros worked on railroads in the eastern and midwestern United States. Also contained in this sub-series are records of the Southern Tenant Farmers Union, National Farm Labor Union, and National Agricultural Workers Union (consolidated into a single file unit, as they are different names for the same union at various stages of its development). The STFU, founded by H.L. Mitchell and Clay East in Tyronza, Arkansas in 1934, was unique in its biracial membership and was one of the first unions to attempt to organize farm labor. The collection includes annual reports and convention proceedings, newsletters and miscellany from the mid-1930s through the mid-1940s. (The records of the STFU are housed at the University of North Carolina Library's Southern Historical Collection. A microfilm of the collection and a printed guide are available in the Microtext Room, Green Library.) The STFU arrived in California in 1947 at the urging of dust bowl migrants who had settled in the San Joaquin Valley and promptly changed its name to the National Farm Labor Union. Membership was open to all who worked on the land, with collective bargaining to improve wages and working conditions the organization's goal. Galarza joined NFLU in 1948, and the nearly two linear feet of correspondence, notes, reports, flyers and newsletters attest to his rigorous work schedule. By the mid-1950s, he was NAWU's sole representative in California. Among the most revealing documents are Galarza's emotionally-charged correspondence with NAWU president Mitchell and the annual reports, statements, and minutes which demonstrate how union policy was formulated. NAWU merged with the Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butchers Workmen on August 2, 1960. The NAWU-Amalgamated merger negotiations papers reflect H.L. Mitchell's and Galarza's distrust of AFL-CIO leadership. Post-merger correspondence and reports are limited, as Mitchell remained with Amalgamated and Galarza resigned a few months later. The Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee, established by the AFL-CIO in 1959, at first complemented the National Agricultural Workers Union's organizing efforts, but gradually began to siphon off NAWU members. Committee records include correspondence between Galarza and AWOC head Norman Smith, flyers, newsletters, and reports, mostly from 1959-1960. Documentation which pertains to farm labor organizations which Galarza did not work for is arranged alphabetically in the next section. These include the Citizens for Farm Labor (1963-1967), the United Farm Workers (1965-1971), the National Sharecroppers Fund (1947-1962), and the Regional Foreign Labor Operations Advisory Committee (1954-1960), at whose clandestine meetings growers and state government officials manipulated the bracero policies as they saw fit. The remainder of Series III is comprised of records of non-agricultural organizations, including political and cultural groups in which Galarza took part. Among the early groups represented are the American Council of Spanish-Speaking People (1951-1953), Community Service Organization (1949-1967), El Congreso de Pueblos de Habla Espanola (1939), and Mexican-American Movement, Inc. (1944). Considering the extent of Galarza's involvement in certain of these groups (he was, for instance, chairman of the National Committee of La Raza Unida, and served on the board of directors of the Mexican American Legal Defense and Educational Fund, Inc.), the records in this sub-section are surprisingly sparse and mostly secondary in nature.
  - Subseries A: Agricultural Labor
    - Agriculture Workers Organizing Committee, 1959-1966
      - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Flyers and other organizing materials, ca. 1960 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Miscellany, 1963, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Newsclippings, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Newsclippings, 1960 (1) (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Newsclippings, 1960 (2) (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Newsclippings, 1960 (3) (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Newsclippings, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Newsclippings, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Newsletter, "AWOC Organizer," 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Newsletters, "The Agricultural Worker," 1961; "The Harvester," 1962; "AWOC News," 1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Newsletters, California Labor Federation, AFL-CIO, "Weekly News Letter," 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Notes, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Press releases, 1959-1960 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Radio script, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Statements and reports, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Statements and reports, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - U.S. Department of Labor hearing, testimony by C. Al Green, Director of AWOC, Dec. 7, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Amalgamated Meatcutters and Butchers Workment, 1959-1972
      - Activity reports by Galarza, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Correspondence, Apr.-Sept., 1960 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Correspondence, Oct., 1960-1963 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Correspondence, 1969-1972 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      - Miscellany, 1959-1968 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - NAWU-Amalgamated merger agreement, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      - `Staff-grams', 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Pan-American Union, 1940-1949
      - Correspondence, general, 1941-1943 (Box 5, Folder 6)
      - Correspondence, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Correspondence, Jan.-July, 1945 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Correspondence, Aug.-Dec., 1945 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Correspondence, 1946-1949 (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Correspondence with Mexican Embassy, 1941-1942 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Correspondence with Mexican Embassy, 1943-1945 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      - Flores Lopez, Jose, case, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Statements and reports, 1940-1945 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Statements and reports, 1946-1948 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      - Tapia Montana, Felix, case, 1945 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Southern Tenant Farmers Union/National Farm Labor Union/ National Agricultural Workers Union, 1935-1972
      - STFU, 1935-1969
        - Annual reports and convention proceedings, 1935-1942 (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Calendar, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 6)
        - "Complete Proceedings, Trial of Claude C. Williams by the Executive Council, STFU," Sept. 16-17, 1938 (Box 6, Folder 7)
        - "The Disinherited Speak, Letters from Sharecroppers," n.d. (Box 6, Folder 8)
        - "The Founding and Early History of the STFU," H.L. Mitchell, 1973; other articles about the STFU, 1947-1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
        - Johnson v. State of Arkansas, appellant's abstract and brief, Arkansas Supreme Court, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 10)
        - Miscellany, 1935-1943 (Box 6, Folder 11)
        - Newsletters and newspapers, 1935-1941 (Box 6, Folder 12)
        - Speeches by H.L. Mitchell, 1940, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - NFLU/NAWU (California), 1947-1972
        - Activity reports by Galarza, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        - Activity reports by Galarza, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        - Constitutions, 1949-1958 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        - Contracts, 1947-1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        - Conventions, 1947-1957 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        - Correspondence, 1947-June, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 6)
        - Correspondence, Sept., 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
        - Correspondence, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
        - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 9)
        - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 10)
        - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 11)